A Guide to the Additional Papers of Sam Higginbottom and Jane Ethelind Cody Higginbottom 1844-1971
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Additional Papers of Sam Higginbottom and Jane Ethelind Cody Higginbottom 1844-1971
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
5996-b,-c,-d
This collection consists of ca. 13,650 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers are an addition to the main collection (#5996) given by Henry and Elizabeth Higginbotton in 1959 and 1971. The main collection is one that was utilized for the biography by Gary Hess. This collection contains the richest material and most extensive records. This current gift was presented to the University of Virginia in these groups from Dec. 1971 - May 1972 by Mrs. Lynndon Clough and David Higginbottom. Accession number #5996-b came from the estate of Gertrude Higginbotton Wallace of Washington, D.C. Accession numbers #5996-c and #5996-d came from the Higginbottom home in Florida. Material that was judged irrelevant to Higginbottom's missionary activities was returned to the Higginbottom family.
Scope and Content Information
The Higginbottom Papers, 1844-1971, consist of ca. 13,650 items (ca. 13 shelf feet) relating to activities of the Higginbottom family. The collection contains family correspondence and papers pertaining to missionary activities, the Presbyterian Church, and miscellaneous activities of the Higginbottoms. There are some manuscript drafts, proofs, etc., of various published works and reports by Ethel and Sam Higginbottom.
To 1903 the papers chiefly include family correspondence providing interesting background for understanding the missionary life that the Higginbottom's led. From 1903 to 1945 the papers primarily concern Sam and Ethel's activities as missionaries in India and the development of the agricultural institute at Allahabad. Although this material is peripheral to the main collection (See "Acquisition") it offers fascinating insight into the personal life and attitudes of the Higginbottoms'. Satisfactions and frustrations are chronicled through their letters to one another, members of the family, and friends. There is also some interesting information concerning the relationship between the missionary activity and the emergin nationalist sentiment in India. Higginbottom's activities in fund-raising durign his visits to the United States are thoroughly covered, as are Ethel's activities in the States. The post-1945 material pertains to the activities of Sam and Ethel durign their retirement. These papers reflect their continuing attachment to Indian missionary work. They also document the efforts of Sam Higginbottom to found the Christian Service Training Center at Frostproof, Florida during the 1950s.
Sam Higginbotton (1874-1958) came to American from England in 1894 to attend the Mt. Harmon School in Massachusetts. Influenced by the evangelical work of Dwight Lyman Moody, he went to Amherst in 1899 and Princeton in 1901. While at Princeton, he met George Forman, a missionary from India. Forman convinced Higginbotton to go to India as a Presbyterian missionary in 1903. Higginbotton taught at the Allahabad Christian College and was deeply impressed by the poverty of village life. He assumed a leading role in developing the Naini Leper Asylum and conceived the pioneering idea of founding an agricultural school to improve economic conditions on the sub-continent. Ethel and Sam Higginbottom returned to America several times to raise funds for the Allahabad Agricultual Institute. Such visits occurred during 1909-11, 1914-15, 1919-21, 1932-33. The period of greatest development and fufillment for the school was during the 1920s and 1930s. Such prominent Indians such as Gandhi were fascinated by Higginbottom's ideas for the improvement of Indian life. During various periods Higginbottom advised Indian princes concerning agricultural techniques. Throughout his stay in India, Higginbottom remained in close contact with his associates in the Presbyterian Church. His manifold public appearances in search of funds brought them increasing recognition from leaders of the Church. In 1939 Higginbottom was elected Moderator of the Presbyterian Chruch in America.
Higginbottom retired in 1945 and returned to America settling in Frostproof, Florida. Higginbottom kept in close touch with developments in India until his death. During the 1950s he unsuccessfully tried to establish a Christian Service Training Center to train missionaries for agricultural work. During his lifetime Higginbottom was widely known and respected. His biographer has written that he "embodied the ideal American representative in underdeveloped nations." His life and the work of the Institute have been adequately delineated by Gary R. Hess in Sam Higginbottom of Allahabad: Pioneer of Point Four to India,(Charlottesville: U. of Virginia Press, 1967).
Organization
When the material was received it was in no inherent order, either chronologically or topically. Series I, Accission #5996-b, was kept apart from #5996-c and #5996-d (Series II), which were interfiled, and two chronologies were created. However the chronological breakdown does not extend to month and day. The arrangement within the chronology is generally: family papers, missionary papers, Presbyterian Church papers, and general and miscellaneous papers.
Contents List
- Series I, Accession #5996-b
  - Family papers 1915-1920 (Box 1)
  - Missionary papers 1918-1920 (Box 1)
  - Family papers 1921 (Box 1)
  - Family papers 1922, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Family papers 1923 (Box 1)
  - Missionary papers 1923 (Box 1)
  - Family papers 1924 (Box 2)
  - Missionary papers 1924 (Box 2)
  - Family papers 1925 (Box 2)
  - Family papers 1926 (Box 2)
  - Family papers 1927 (Box 2)
  - Family papers 1928 (Box 2)
  - Family papers 1929 (Box 2)
  - Family papers 1930 (Box 2)
  - Family papers 1931 (Box 3)
  - Family papers 1932-1933 (Box 3)
  - Family papers 1934 (Box 3)
  - Missionary papers 1934-1936 (Box 3)
  - Family papers 1935 (Box 3)
  - Family papers 1936 (Box 3)
  - Family papers 1937-1939 (Box 3)
  - Missionary papers 1937-1939 (Box 3)
  - Family papers 1940-1942 (Box 4)
  - Missionary papers 1940-1942 (Box 4)
  - Family papers 1943-1946 (Box 4)
  - Family papers 1947-1955 (Box 4)
  - Family papers 1956-1957 (Box 4)
  - Family papers 1958-1959 (Box 4)
  - Missionary papers 1958-1959 (Box 4)
  - Family papers 1960-1962 (Box 4)
  - Family papers 1963-1966 (Box 4)
  - Family papers 1966-1970 (Box 4)
  - Family papers n.d. (Box 4)
  - Missionary papers n.d. (Box 4)
  - 16 vols. including scrapbooks, genealogy, diaries, and financial records, 1916, 1936-1937 19th and 20th Cent., printed material (Box 5)
  - issues of Allabad Farmer, Ewing magazine, National Christian Council review, and Visitor's Books, 1916-1950, also miscellaneous 20th Cent., printed material, ca. 30 items (Box 6)
  - Harijan news sheet 1939-1948, printed material (Box 7)
  - varous news sheets 1927-1965, printed material (Box 8)
  - Gen. Presbyterian Church 1939-1960, printed material (Box 9)
  - Indian Missions 1930-1970, printed material (Box 9)
  - India 1930-1970, printed material (Box 9)
  - India maps n.d., printed material (Box 9)
  - Articles and published works of Higginbottoms 1917-1962, printed material (Box 10)
  - Naini Leper Asylum 1924-1940, printed material (Box 10)
  - Christian Training Center 1956, printed material (Box 10)
  - Allahabad Agricultural Institute 1930-1970, printed material (Box 11)
  - Biographical re Sam Higginbottom 1930-1979, printed material (Box 12)
  - Genealogical 1930-1970, printed material (Box 12)
- Series II, Accession #5996-c and #5996-d
  - Family papers 1844-1897 (Box 1)
  - Family papers 1898-1899 (Box 1)
  - Family papers 1900-1901 (Box 1)
  - Family papers 1902 (Box 1)
  - Family papers 1903 (Box 1)
  - Family papers 1904, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Family papers 1905, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Family papers 1906, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Family papers 1907, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Family papers 1907 (Box 3)
  - Family papers 1908, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Family papers 1909 (Box 3)
  - Family papers 1910 (Box 3)
  - Papers re: India 1910 (Box 3)
  - Family papers 1912, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Family papers 1913, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Family papers 1914 (Box 4)
  - Family papers 1915 (Box 4)
  - Family papers 1916 (Box 5)
  - Family papers 1917 (Box 5)
  - Budget (Agricultural Department, Gwalior State) 1917-1918 (Box 5)
  - Family papers 1918-1919 (Box 5)
  - Papers re: India 1918-1919 (Box 5)
  - Family papers 1920 (Box 5)
  - Presbyterian papers 1920 (Box 6)
  - Family papers 1921-1922 (Box 6)
  - Missionary papers 1921-1922 (Box 6)
  - Family papers 1923 (Box 6)
  - Missionary papers 1923 (Box 6)
  - Family papers 1924 (Box 6)
  - Missionary papers 1924 (Box 6)
  - Presbyterian papers 1925-1926 (Box 6)
  - Family papers 1925-1927 (Box 6)
  - Missionary papers 1925-1927 (Box 6)
  - Family papers 1928-1929 (Box 7)
  - Missionary papers 1928-1929 (Box 7)
  - Missionary papers 1930 (Box 7)
  - Family papers 1930-1931 (Box 7)
  - Family and Missionary papers 1931-1932 (Box 7)
  - Family papers 1933 (Box 7)
  - Missionary papers 1933 (Box 7)
  - Family papers 1934-1935 (Box 7)
  - Missionary papers 1934-1935 (Box 7)
  - Family papers 1936 (Box 8)
  - Missionary papers 1936 (Box 8)
  - Family papers 1937 (Box 8)
  - Missionary papers 1937 (Box 8)
  - Presbyterian papers 1937 (Box 8)
  - Presbyterian papers 1938, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Papers re: India 1938 (Box 8)
  - Family papers 1939 (Box 9)
  - Presbyterian papers 1939, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Family papers 1940 (Box 9)
  - Missionary papers 1940, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Family papers 1941 (Box 10)
  - Missionary papers 1941, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Family papers 1942 (Box 10)
  - Missionary papers 1942, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Family papers 1943 (Box 10)
  - Missionary papers 1943, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Family papers 1944 (Box 11)
  - Papers re: India 1944, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Family papers 1945, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Missionary papers 1945 (Box 12)
  - Papers re: India 1945 (Box 12)
  - Family papers 1946 (Box 12)
  - Missionary papers 1946, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Missionary papers 1946 (Box 13)
  - Family papers 1947 (Box 13)
  - Missionary papers 1947 (Box 13)
  - Papers re: India 1947, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Hungry for Love 1947, Ms (Box 13)
  - Family papers 1948 (Box 13)
  - Papers re: India 1948, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Brother's Blood 1948, Ms (Box 14)
  - Family papers 1949 (Box 14)
  - Missionary papers 1949 (Box 14)
  - Missionary papers 1949 (Box 15)
  - Christian Service Training Center 1949 (Box 15)
  - M.A. Thesis of K.S. Pandit 1949, Ms (Box 15)
  - Family papers 1950 (Box 15)
  - Missionary papers 1950 (Box 15)
  - Missionary papers 1950 (Box 16)
  - Mss drafts 1950 (Box 16)
  - Family papers 1951 (Box 16)
  - Missionary papers 1951 (Box 16)
  - Family papers 1952 (Box 16)
  - Missionary papers 1952 (Box 16)
  - Christian Service Training Center 1952 (Box 16)
  - Family papers 1953 (Box 17)
  - Missionary papers 1953 (Box 17)
  - Christian Service Training Center 1953 (Box 17)
  - Mrs. Sam Higginbottom, The 'Professoress' in India[1953], Ms (Box 17)
  - Family papers 1954 (Box 17)
  - Missionary papers 1954 (Box 17)
  - Christian Service Training Center 1954 (Box 17)
  - Family papers 1955 (Box 17)
  - Missionary papers 1955 (Box 18)
  - Christian Service Center 1955 (Box 18)
  - Map of Allahabad Institute 1955 (Box 18)
  - Family papers 1956 (Box 18)
  - Christian Service Training Center 1956 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous papers 1956 (Box 18)
  - Family papers 1957 (Box 18)
  - Missionary papers 1957 (Box 18)
  - Ms by Ethel Higginbottom 1957 (Box 18)
  - Family papers 1958 (Box 19)
  - Missionary papers 1958 (Box 19)
  - Papers re: Death of Sam Higginbottom 1958, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Papers re: Death of Sam Higginbottom 1958, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous papers 1958 (Box 20)
  - Family papers 1959 (Box 20)
  - Agricultural Institute papers 1959 (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous papers 1959 (Box 20)
  - Family papers 1960 (Box 21)
  - Agricultural Institute papers 1960 (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous papers 1960, 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Family papers 1961 (Box 21)
  - Agricultural Institute papers 1961 (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous papers 1961 (Box 21)
  - Family papers 1962 (Box 22)
  - Papers re: India 1962 (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous papers 1962 (Box 22)
  - Family papers 1963 (Box 22)
  - Papers re: India 1963 (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous papers 1963 (Box 22)
  - Family papers 1964 (Box 23)
  - Papers re: India 1964 (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous papers 1964 (Box 23)
  - Family papers 1965 (Box 23)
  - Papers re: India 1965 (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous papers 1965 (Box 23)
  - Family papers 1966 (Box 23)
  - Papers re: India 1966 (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous papers 1966 (Box 23)
  - Papers re: India 1967 (Box 23)
  - Miscellaneous papers 1967 (Box 23)
  - Papers re: India, and miscellaneous papers 1968 (Box 24)
  - Papers re: India 1969 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous papers 1969 (Box 24)
  - Papers re: India 1970 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous papers 1970-1971 (Box 24)
  - Papers re: India 1971 (Box 24)
  - Missionary papers n.d., 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Missionary papers n.d., 2 folders (Box 25)
  - presumably by Ethel Cody Higginbottom n.d., 13 Mss (Box 25)
  - presumably by Ethel Cody Higginbottom n.d., 10 Mss (Box 25)
  - re: Ethel Cody Higginbottom n.d., ca. 8 Mss (Box 25)
  - Missionary papers n.d., 4 folders (Box 26)
  - re: India n.d., ca. 15 Mss (Box 26)
  - Family photos n.d. (Box 27)
  - Photos of Higginbottoms at Allahabad n.d. (Box 27)
  - Photos of Ethel, Sam, and group photos n.d. (Box 27)
  - Photos of Christian Training Center n.d. (Box 27)
  - Photos of Allahabad n.d. (Box 27)